Guide to the Livingston Family Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
- Henry H. and Mary Eleanor Curran Livingston Papers, 1886-1969; Series VII; 5.5; (14 boxes)
  - Photographs
    - Livingston children, circa 1918-1946 (Box 57, Folder 500)
      Includes Eleanor Livingston with children Henry and Eleanor, and portrait of all three in military uniforms; also includes a letter from General H.H. Arnold.
    - Livingston, Henry H., 1906-1947, undated (Box 58, Folder 501-503)
      Includes images from Yale University and U.S. Army years
    - Livingston, Mary Eleanor Curran
      - Portraits, circa 1886-1950 (Box 58, Folder 504-507)
      - Portraits with friends, circa 1890-1900 (Box 58, Folder 508)
      - Portraits of friends, circa 1915 (Box 58, Folder 509)
    - Family snapshot photographs, with negatives, 1947-1950s (Box 59, Folder 510-514)
      In original folders, arranged as received
    - Family snapshot photographs, with negatives, 1947-1950s (Box 60, Folder 515-516)
    - Miscellaneous, undated (Box 60, Folder 517)
- Henry H. and Maria Burroughs Livingston Papers, 1840-2003; Series VIII; 7; (18 boxes) + 1 broadside folder
  Series VIII is organized into four subseries: Correspondence, Personal Papers, Livingston Family History Files, and Other Subject Files.
  Henry H. Livingston (1918–2008)
  Henry Hopkins Livingston Jr. was born in New York City on March 16, 1918, the son of Henry Hopkins Livingston (1887-1960) and Mary Eleanor Curran Livingston. He was educated at Friends Seminary in New York and the Hotchkiss School in Lakeville, Connecticut (1936), before graduating from Yale University in 1940 and receiving a Certificate of Transportation from Yale in 1941. During World War II, Livingston served in the United States Army Air Corps (1941-1946) with tours of duty with Air Transport in North Africa and the Middle East. After discharge, he spent a decade with the Boston and Maine Railroad and then the Maine Central Railroad, followed by positions with the investment banking firms of Morgan Stanley, Clark Dodge, Kidder Peabody, Brown Brothers Harriman, and Paine Webber, before retiring in 1996. Henry Livingston died on November 25, 2008.
  Maria May Burroughs Livingston (1919–)
  In January 1942 Livingston married Maria May Burroughs (b. April 8, 1919), daughter of Richard H. and Isabel Black Burroughs of Richmond, Virginia. The great-granddaughter of the painter Frederic Edwin Church, Oak Hill's northern neighbor, she attended the Collegiate School in New York, and graduated from Sweet Briar College in 1940. The couple had four children: Isabel Church Livingston (b.1943), Henry H. Livingston III (b.1945), Richard H. B. Livingston (b.1947), and Catharine Van Brugh Livingston (b. 1949, married Robert Edmonds).
  The Livingstons maintained a home in New York City in addition to Oak Hill.
  The series contains some correspondence and personal papers, but is largely composed of research files assembled by Henry and Maria Livingston on family history and other topics. He was directly involved in the Livingston Manor Tercentenary celebrations of 1986, and collected historical material on Livingston homes and estates in the Hudson Valley, in addition to Oak Hill. Also here are files of reference material and correspondence about the family compiled by Columbia County Historian Walter V. Miller (1903-1980) and his successor Elaine Bohnsack Liepshutz (1920-2001); they appear to be the historians' own correspondence files, and their presence in the family papers is not explained. In addition, Liepshutz's files contain sets of photocopies of translations from the Dutch of letters between Robert Livingston (1654-1728) and his wife Alida Schuyler Van Rensselaer (1656-1729), and letters to the Livingston from others including Steven van Cortlandt. See the subseries Livingston Family History Files for further information about these transcripts.
  The Personal Papers subseries holds several files of material documenting Henry Livingston's training and tour of duty in the United States Army Air Corps.
  - Correspondence
    - Klein, Milton M., 1958-1960 (Box 61, Folder 518)
    - Liepshutz, Elaine B., 1977-1993, undated (Box 61, Folder 519)
    - Livingston, Eleanor Mulford [sister], 1931-1950, undated (Box 61, Folder 520)
      Includes formal portrait photographs
    - Livingston, Mary Eleanor Curran (1884-1969) [mother], 1964-1968 (Box 61, Folder 521)
    - Yale University, 2001, undated (Box 61, Folder 522)
    - Livingston family history inquiries, miscellaneous, 1961-2000 (Box 61, Folder 523)
    - Condolence notes, 1969 (Box 61, Folder 524-525)
    - General correspondence, 1925-2003 (Box 61, Folder 526-527)
    - Miscellaneous papers, 2001-2002 (Box 61, Folder 528)
  - Personal papers
    - Antiques, 1934-1987, undated (Box 62, Folder 529-530)
      Includes appraisal of the estate of Mary Eleanor Livingston, and notebook with inventory of family antiques and decorative arts; notebook microfilmed in 2007 (Beinecke film # 2915)
    - Family [children and grandchildren] material, 1955-2001 (Box 62, Folder 531)
    - Fauconnier cabinet [estate inquiry], 1982, undated (Box 62, Folder 532)
    - Heritage societies, 1953-2001 (Box 62, Folder 533)
    - Hotchkiss School group portrait, circa 1936
    - Livingston, Henry: media coverage and snapshot with dog, 1980-2002 (Box 62, Folder 534)
    - New York Infirmary centennial celebration, 1975 (Box 62, Folder 535)
    - Obituaries [family members and others], 1967, 1972, undated (Box 62, Folder 536)
    - Paintings, 1959-2003, undated (Box 62, Folder 537)
    - Ramshorn-Livingston Sanctuary, 1974-1993 (Box 62, Folder 538)
    - Sloop Eleanor, 1999 (Box 62, Folder 539)
    - Yale University class notebook, 1937-1938 (Box 63)
      Illustrated history essay written for Yale course Architecture 10
    - Military service papers, 1942-1951 (Box 64, Folder 540-549)
      Includes World War II military forms and certificates, pilot training manuals, flight logs, and miscellaneous records, with one folder of newspaper clippings
    - Military service papers, 1942-1951 (Box 65, Folder 550-555)
    - Miscellaneous papers, 1918-2001 (Box 65, Folder 556)
  - Livingston family history files
    - Allen, James, journal [1770s, photocopy of typescript], undated (Box 65, Folder 557)
    - Cholly Knickerbocker (Igor Cassini) columns, undated (Box 65, Folder 558)
    - Columbia County historians' files, 1876-1990s (Box 66, Folder 559-566)
      Research and correspondence files compiled by Walter V. Miller and Elaine B. Liepshutz
    - Columbia County historians' files, 1876-1990s (Box 67, Folder 567-574)
    - Columbia County historians' files, 1876-1990s (Box 68, Folder 575-576)
    - Genealogies (includes other families), undated (Box 68, Folder 577)
    - Livingston family burial vaults, undated (Box 68, Folder 578)
    - Livingston family gatherings (reunions), 1981-1996 (Box 68, Folder 579)
    - Livingston family houses
      - Clermont and Idele, 1981-2003 (Box 68, Folder 580)
      - Hermitage, 1964-1992 (Box 68, Folder 581)
      - Oak Hill, 1889-1979, undated (Box 68, Folder 582-584)
        Includes two folders of photographs: house and grounds; and interiors; also includes pieces of wallpaper removed from house hallways in 1988
      - Miscellaneous, 1902-2000 (Box 69, Folder 585)
    - Livingston hatchment (photograph), undated
    - Livingston Manor, 1850-1974, undated (Box 69, Folder 586-587)
      Includes Deduction of the Title to the Manor of Livingston (1850)
    - Livingston Manor Tercentenary, 1985-1986 (Box 69, Folder 588-593)
      Includes papers from symposium
    - Livingston Manor Tercentenary, 1985-1986 (Box 70, Folder 594-598)
      Primarily drafts of A Portrait of Livingston Manor, by Ruth Piwonka (1986)
    - Livingston manuscripts offered for sale by dealers, undated (Box 70, Folder 599)
    - Livingston Memorial Church, 1970-1985, undated (Box 70, Folder 600)
    - Livingston, Montgomery, 1980 (Box 70, Folder 601)
      Includes copies of The Landscape Art of Montgomery Livingston, by Ruth Piwonka (1980)
    - Livingstons in New York City, 1899-1974,undated (Box 71, Folder 602)
      Includes material on Moses Rogers house, State Street
    - Livingston family papers in other repositories, undated (Box 71, Folder 603)
    - Livingston-Redmond papers correspondence
      Primarily photocopies of translations of Dutch-language letters written between Robert and Alida Livingston when he traveled to Albany or New York City, and she remained in the Hudson Valley managing their affairs. One of the two sets of transcripts was annotated by Elaine Liepshutz. The translations were made in the late 1970s while the Livingston-Redmond Papers were on deposit at the Franklin Delano Roosevelt Library, in Hyde Park, New York. The papers were purchased in 1993 by the Gilder Lehrman Institute of American History, New York, New York, and cataloged as the Livingston-Redmond Family Archive (1637-1850).
      - Administrative file [with collection finding aid], circa 1980 (Box 71, Folder 604)
      - Letters between the Livingstons, 1680-1726: primary set, circa 1980 (Box 71, Folder 605-612)
      - Letters between the Livingstons, 1680-1726: primary set, circa 1980 (Box 72, Folder 613-617)
      - Letters from others to Livingston, 1681-1700, circa 1980 (Box 72, Folder 618)
      - Letters between the Livingstons, 1680-1726: annotated set, circa 1980, 1993 (Box 72, Folder 619-621)
      - Letters between the Livingstons, 1680-1726: annotated set, circa 1980, 1993 (Box 73, Folder 622-626)
    - Livingston, Robert (1654-1728) [first Lord of the Manor], 1957-1971, undated (Box 74, Folder 627)
      Includes Walter Miller's series in the Chatham Courier
    - Livingston, Robert R. (1746-1813) [Chancellor], 1946, undated (Box 74, Folder 628)
    - Mining, 1875-1992, undated (Box 74, Folder 629)
      Includes By-laws of the Hudson River Spathic Iron Ore Company (1875)
    - Ripley, Mary Livingston (1914-1996), 1996, undated (Box 74, Folder 630)
    - Wilson, Magrieta Livingston (1904-2004), 1926-1942, 1988 (Box 74, Folder 631)
    - Livingstons, miscellaneous, 1899-2000, undated (Box 74, Folder 632-636)
      Includes full photocopy of Memoir of Mrs. Edward Livingston by Louise Hunt (New York: 1886)
    - Livingstons, miscellaneous, 1899-2000, undated (Box 75, Folder 637-641)
      Includes articles on the family published in contemporary popular periodicals
  - Other subject files
    - Casement, Dan Dillon, undated (Box 75, Folder 642)
    - Catskill-Greendale Ferry, undated (Box 75, Folder 643)
    - Cole/Kool family, undated (Box 75, Folder 644)
    - Fulton postage stamp, 1965 (Box 75, Folder 645)
    - Hudson Valley miscellaneous, 1889-2002 (Box 75, Folder 646)
    - Hudson Valley miscellaneous, 1889-2002 (Box 76, Folder 647-648)
    - Indians, 2000-2003 (Box 76, Folder 649)
    - Kidd, William, 1941-1981, undated (Box 76, Folder 650)
    - Langford, Nathaniel, 1890, undated (Box 76, Folder 651)
    - Olana [Frederic Edwin Church home], 1965-1999 (Box 76, Folder 652)
    - Olmsted-Astor lawsuit, [1928] (Box 76, Folder 653)
    - Rolls-Royce, 1925-1968 (Box 76, Folder 654)
    - Schooners, steamboats, and ships, 1874-1991, undated (Box 76, Folder 655)
      Includes stereographs of steamships
    - Scottish history, 1957-2000, undated (Box 656)
    - Trains and coaches, 1840-1980, undated (Box 77, Folder 657-658)
      Includes a folder of 19th-century stereographs of trains and stage coaches, and Act of Incorporation of the Albany and West Stockbridge Rail-road Company (Albany: 1840)
    - United States history, miscellaneous, 1901-2001 (Box 77, Folder 659-660)
    - Van Deusen family, 1999 (Box 77, Folder 661)
    - Van Rensselaer family, 1894, 1984, undated (Box 77, Folder 662)
    - Miscellaneous clippings, 1905-1986, undated (Box 77, Folder 663)
    - Miscellaneous manuscripts and typescripts, 1857-1924, undated (Box 77, Folder 664)
    - Miscellaneous photographs [unidentified], undated (Box 77, Folder 665)
    - Miscellaneous postcards, 1920s-1930s, undated (Box 78, Folder 666-667)
- Oak Hill Iron Mining Company Records, 1879-1889; Series IX; 2.5; (6 boxes)
  Series IX is organized into two subseries: Correspondence, and Bound Volumes.
  Oak Hill Iron Mining Company
  Oak Hill Iron Mining Company was a short-lived venture of Herman Livingston (1856-1936) to remove spathic iron ore from family properties at Mt. Thomas (on the Long Hill ridge located south of the city of Hudson), and move it by a small-gauge gravity railroad down to the family's dock on the Hudson River for shipment to foundries in New York and Pennsylvania. Livingston's father, Herman T. Livingston (1827-1899), and his maternal uncle Edmund Pendleton Rogers (1827-1895) and cousin Archibald Rogers (1852-1928) of Hyde Park, New York, were principal investors in the company. Also known as the Livingston Mine, the property was eventually sold to the Burden family of Troy, New York, and operations were consolidated with Burden's nearby Hudson River Ore and Iron Company.
  The series holds the business records of the company. The Correspondence Files, which also contain many invoices and receipts, document the Livingston family's relationships with geologists, chemists, transporters, foundries, manufacturers, and vendors in New York and Pennsylvania. A single "Japanese Letter Copying Book" holds Herman Livingston's outgoing correspondence from the company's earliest years, and the folder for Rossiter W. Raymond contains a copy in Livingston's hand of Raymond's 1876 study of spathic iron ores of the Hudson River. Noted geologist Nathaniel Southgate Shaler wrote a full report on the mine; it is filed in with his letters. The Bound Volumes subseries includes the company's accounting records of various types and formats, as well as time and payroll books which aggregate the personnel costs of the mining and roasting of ore, blacksmithing, and the construction of the necessary rail lines, kilns, and docks.
  Herman T. Livingston's daily journal, filed in Series II, includes some notes on mine activities. Correspondence from H.T. Livingston to Herman Livingston is found in Series III.
  - Correspondence
    - Copy book of outgoing correspondence, 1881-1882 (Box 79, Folder 668)
    - Albany & Rensselaer Iron and Steel Company, 1881-1884 (Box 79, Folder 669)
    - American Institute of Mining Engineers, 1882-1884 (Box 79, Folder 670)
    - Atlantic Dynamite Company, 1882-1884 (Box 79, Folder 671)
    - Baurhyte, Charles A., 1879-1887 (Box 79, Folder 672)
    - Brown, J. Romaine, 1881-1884 (Box 79, Folder 673)
    - Clapp & Jones Manufacturing Company, 1883-1884 (Box 79, Folder 674)
    - Day & Holt, 1883-1884 (Box 79, Folder 675)
    - Dupont's Powder Agency, 1883-1884 (Box 79, Folder 676)
    - E. Lampman, 1882-1885 (Box 79, Folder 677)
    - Fairbanks & Company, 1883-1884 (Box 79, Folder 678)
    - Francis Starrs, 1882-1884 (Box 79, Folder 679)
    - Gifford Brothers, 1883-1884 (Box 79, Folder 680)
    - Henry W. Trowbridge, 1882-1883 (Box 79, Folder 681)
    - George W. Holdridge, 1882-1884 (Box 79, Folder 682)
    - Ingersoll Rock Drill Company, 1882-1884 (Box 79, Folder 683-684)
    - J. D. Goodwin, 1883-1884 (Box 80, Folder 685)
    - John B. Dallas, 1881-1884 (Box 80, Folder 686-691)
    - Lebanon Manufacturing Company, 1883-1884 (Box 81, Folder 692)
    - Lee, Charles Tennant, 1883-1884 (Box 81, Folder 693)
    - Ledoux & Ricketts, 1881-1883 (Box 81, Folder 694)
    - Lehigh & Wilkes-Barre Coal Company, 1881-1884 (Box 81, Folder 695)
    - Pottstown Iron Company, 1882-1884 (Box 81, Folder 696)
    - Pottsville Iron and Steel Company, 1881-1882 (Box 81, Folder 697)
    - R. B. Benedict Company, 1883-1884 (Box 81, Folder 698)
    - Raymond, Rossiter W., undated (Box 81, Folder 699)
    - Shaler, Nathaniel Southgate, 1883-1884 (Box 81, Folder 700)
    - Sheafer, P. W. (Peter Wenrick), 1880-1883 (Box 81, Folder 701)
    - Simons & Richards, 1882-1884 (Box 81, Folder 702)
    - Snyder, Louis, 1882-1883 (Box 81, Folder 703)
    - Starrs & King, 1881-1882 (Box 81, Folder 704)
    - Tubular Barrow & Machine Company, 1882-1884 (Box 81, Folder 705)
    - Washburn and Company, 1881-1884 (Box 81, Folder 706)
    - Washburn & Moen, 1882 (Box 81, Folder 707)
    - William Denny, 1884 (Box 82, Folder 708)
    - William Fuller & Sons, 1882-1883 (Box 82, Folder 709)
    - General, A-Z, 1881-1884 (Box 82, Folder 710-718)
  - Bound volumes
    - Financial records
      - Cash book, 1881-1883 (Box 82, Folder 719)
      - Cash book, 1882-1884 (Box 83, Folder 720)
      - Cash book, 1884-1889
      - Day book, 1882-1884 (Box 83, Folder 721)
      - Day book, 1884-1889
      - Journal, 1882-1884 (Box 83, Folder 722)
      - Journal, 1884-1889
      - Ledger, 1881-1883 (Box 84, Folder 723)
      - Ledger, with separate index, 1884-1889
      - Time book and payroll record, 1882-1886 (Box 84, Folder 724-726)
    - Miscellaneous records
      - Ledger recording "Ore mined and hauled," and "Coal sold", 1881-1885 (Box 84, Folder 727)
      - Stock certificate register, 1884 (Box 84, Folder 728)
- Paramount Oil Company Records, 1919-1961; Series X; 2.5; (6 boxes)
  Series X is organized into two subseries: Correspondence and Legal Files, and Financial Records.
  Paramount Oil Company
  The Paramount Oil Company was a distributor of petroleum products, supplying gasoline and kerosene to service stations and repair garages, and fuel and furnace oil to factories, institutions, and private homes in Columbia and Dutchess counties. It was incorporated in Jersey City, New Jersey, in 1919, by principals Herbert W. Lorenz, Edward A. Martin, and William P. Martin. Wesley F. Lorenz (1894-1981) was appointed president and general manager of the corporation. By 1923 the company had operations in Hudson, New York, and by December 1924 Herman Livingston (1856-1936) had become a stockholder and a director. In 1926 his son Henry H. Livingston also became a director; Herman Livingston became company president in 1927, succeeded at his death by his son Herman Jr. The Paramount Oil Company continued into the 1960s, but at that point the family's involvement was mainly in the land along the Hudson River that it had leased to Paramount to hold storage tanks. The Livingstons founded the Paramount Tank Corporation in 1928; the records of this company are intermixed with those of the Paramount Oil Company.
  Series X holds the business records of the Paramount Oil Company and the Livingston family's Paramount Tank Corporation. The subseries Correspondence and Legal Files contains incorporation records and minutes, letters, internal memoranda, legal agreements, leases, contracts, and insurance policies. The files document the company's founding, stockholders, and administration, and agreements with land owners, subcontractors, and national corporations such as the Sinclair Refining Company. Also in the files are a few maps showing pipelines, blueprints of buildings, and photographs of gasoline filling stations. The Financial Records subseries holds two folders of papers, but primarily consists of bound ledgers. Additional material relating to Herman Livingston's personal financial crisis, precipitated by bad loans made to Wesley Lorenz, can be found in his son's files: Series VI, Herman and Olga Livingston Papers.
  - Correspondence and legal files
    - Minute book, 1919-1927 (Box 85, Folder 729)
    - Invoices (blank) pad, 1930 (Box 85, Folder 730)
    - General files, 1919-1961 (Box 85, Folder 731-735)
    - General files, 1919-1961 (Box 86, Folder 736-744)
    - General files, 1919-1961 (Box 87, Folder 745-751)
  - Financial records
    - Product inventory, 1929 (Box 87, Folder 752)
    - Lorenz loans, 1924-1928 (Box 87, Folder 753)
      See also: Box 44, folder 387
    - Miscellaneous papers, 1924-1936 (Box 87, Folder 754)
    - Stock ledgers, 1919-1931 (Box 88, Folder 755-756)
    - Bills payable ledger, 1927-1929 (Box 88, Folder 757)
    - Cash books, 1928-1929 (Box 88, Folder 758-759)
    - General ledgers, 1928-1931 (Box 89, Folder 760-762)
    - Accounts receivable, Poughkeepsie area, 1931-1932 (Box 89, Folder 763)
    - Stock certificate books (4), 1919-1930 (Box 90)
      Contains volumes of certificates for stock issued: capital (1), common (1), and preferred (2)
- Curran and Mulford Family Papers, 1770-1966; Series XI; 11; (28 boxes) + 2 broadside folders
  Series XI is organized into five subseries: Curran Family Papers, John Elliott Curran Papers, Eliza Mulford Curran Papers, Henry H. Curran Papers, and Mulford Family Papers.
  Edward Curran (1803–1856)
  Edward Curran was an American-born leather goods merchant in Utica, New York, the seventh of ten children of Henry Curran, a tanner who had emigrated from Ireland to central New York State around 1800. Edward was married twice, first to Amanda Bartlett (1807-1837), with whom he had five children: Celia, Charles, Amanda, Edward, and Horatio. With his second wife Mary Jane Langford (1815-1893) he also had five: George, Henry, Philip, Mary (Molly), and John Elliott. Two Curran siblings, Henry and Philip, fought in the American Civil War; Philip survived but Henry did not. Born in 1841, Henry Hastings Curran left Hamilton College in 1861 to enlist in the 146th New York Volunteers, was commissioned a lieutenant colonel, and was killed at the battle of the Wilderness on May 5, 1864. He was memorialized through a privately published biography (see box 91, folders 768-769) three years after his death.
  John Elliot Curran (1848–1890)
  John Elliott Curran was born May 25, 1848, in Utica, New York, the son of Edward and Mary Langford Curran. Known as Jack, he attended Williston Academy in Easthampton, Massachusetts, before enrolling at Yale College, where he was a member of Scroll and Key and rowed on the college crew team. After his 1870 graduation, Curran spent a year in Europe with three Yale classmates; on return he entered law school at Columbia University, and afterward practiced in New York City with George F. Lincoln (Yale 1870). Writing was, however, a greater passion, and Curran soon abandoned his career to become a full-time journalist. His first published pieces had appeared in the Yale Literary Magazine, and by the 1880s his essays and stories were featured in the New Englander (New Haven), Scribner's, Century, and Harper's Monthly magazines. He also wrote for the New York Lumber Trade Journal, Forest and Stream (owned and edited by his Yale classmate George Bird Grinnell), and the Christian Union, and was a literary and drama critic for the Press (New York, NY). Curran's single published novel was Miss Frances Merley (Boston: Cupples and Hurd, 1888). A brief bibliography of his writings can be found in his entry in the Biographical Record of the Class of Seventy, Yale College, 1870-1904. John Elliott Curran was married on May 27, 1875, to Eliza (Lilla) Phillips Mulford of New York; the couple had three children: Henry Hastings (1877-1966), Gerald (Jay) Mulford (1879-1960), and Mary Eleanor (married Henry H. Livingston; see Series VII). Curran died of heart failure at age 47 on May 18, 1890, in his home in Englewood, New Jersey, following a severe case of pneumonia, and was buried in Forest Hill Cemetery, Utica, New York, with the Curran and Langford families.
  Eliza (Lilla) Phillips Mulford Curran (1852–1936)